Guide to the William Sloane Coffin, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Sloane Coffin, Jr. papers
1916-2006
MS 1665
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
80.8
(260 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, subject files, writings, clippings, audio and video recordings, and other materials that document the career of William Sloane Coffin, Jr. The collection includes documentation relating to the civil rights movement, Vietnam War protests, amnesty for war resisters, the Peace Corps, Operation Crossroads Africa, and Yale University during the time when Coffin served as chaplain of Yale University.
Coffin, William Sloane, Jr., 1924-2006
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Sloane Coffin, Jr., 1994, 2000, 2004. Transferred from Battell Chapel, 2004. Gift of Michael Ferber, 2005. Transferred from the Chaplain's Office, 2007. Gift of Randy Wilson Coffin, 2009. Transferred from Yale Divinity Library, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
As established by Yale Corporation regulations, box 38 of the original accession is restricted until January 1, 2044; box 3 of Accession 2007-M-068 is restricted until January 1, 2047; box 3 of Accession 2007-M-084 is restricted until January 1, 2051.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and nine additions: I. Correspondence, 1940-1983. II. Subject Files, 1959-1987. III. Yale University Files, 1955-1977. IV. Writings, 1945-1984. V. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1938-1982.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the career of William Sloane Coffin, Jr., best known as chaplain of Yale University, as senior minister of Riverside Church, and as a political activist. The collection consists of correspondence, topical files, writings, personal papers, audio recordings, videotapes, and other materials created and collected by Coffin. The collection includes ample documentation of the role Coffin played in social and political movements including civil rights, Vietnam War protests, amnesty for draft resisters, disarmament, and international relief work. The following specific groups and organizations are particularly well represented: Operation Crossroads Africa, Peace Corps, Americans For Re-Appraisal of Far Eastern Policy, and Clergy and Laity Concerned about Vietnam. The papers include many other files related to Coffin's involvement in Vietnam War protest and civil rights, particularly his organizing of northern students. Materials relating to Coffin's ministry as chaplain of Yale and as senior minister of Riverside Church, specifically many of his sermons, are also included. Speeches and other writings comprise another significant part of the collection and provide researchers with insight into Coffin's views on a variety of social, political, and religious themes. The collection also includes a small amount of personal and family papers.
Biographical / Historical
William Sloane Coffin, Jr. was born June 1, 1924, in New York City. He attended Deerfield Academy and Phillips Academy Andover before beginning his studies at Yale University in 1942. After one year at Yale, Coffin joined the U.S. Army, in which he served until 1947, when he returned to Yale, graduating with a B.A. in 1949. He went on to study for a year at Union Theological Seminary before joining the Central Intelligence Agency in 1950. In 1953, Coffin began studies at the Yale Divinity School, which he completed in 1956, when he was ordained into the Presbyterian ministry. Coffin spent successive years as the chaplain of Phillips Academy and Williams College before returning to Yale to serve as chaplain from 1957 to 1975. While chaplain at Yale, Coffin became a public figure active in the civil rights movement and protests of U.S. military actions in Vietnam. Coffin served as senior minister of Riverside Church in New York City from 1977 to 1987, when he became president of SANE/FREEZE. Coffin retired to Vermont in the mid-1990s, but remained active as a teacher, lecturer, and writer. He died on April 12, 2006, in Strafford, Vermont.
Biographical / Historical
William Sloane Coffin, Jr. was born on June 1, 1924, in New York City to William Sloane Coffin, Sr. and Catherine Butterfield Coffin. After the death of Coffin's father in 1933, the family moved to Carmel, California, where William attended public school until the ninth grade, when he attended Deerfield Academy in Deerfield, Massachusetts. He spent the following year in Paris with his family, studying to be a concert pianist with Nadia Boulanger. With the outbreak of World War II in 1939, the Coffins returned to the United States, and Coffin completed his high school education at Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts, graduating in 1942.
Coffin attended Yale University School of Music for one year before enlisting in the United States Army. Coffin served in the army until 1947, rising to the rank of captain while working as a liaison with the French and Soviet armies. He returned to the university upon his discharge and received his B.A. in 1949. Coffin spent the next year studying at Union Theological Seminary, then joined the Central Intelligence Agency for a three year period. Coffin returned to Yale once again in 1953, this time attending the divinity school, from which he received a B.D. in 1956. That same year he was ordained as Presbyterian minister. Coffin then served as chaplain of Phillips Andover Academy and Williams College in successive one year periods, before returning to Yale in 1958 to succeed Sidney Lovett as university chaplain, a position he held until 1975.
While chaplain at Yale, Coffin emerged as a public figure involved in numerous prominent events, activities, and organizations. He became involved in international relief work, beginning with Operation Crossroads Africa. On behalf of that group, he led a group of students to Guinea in the summer of 1960. The following year, Coffin was appointed to the President's Advisory Committee on the Peace Corps and established its training program. He trained the first group of Peace Corps volunteers in Puerto Rico during the summer of 1961.
Coffin also became a prominent figure in the civil rights movement in the early 1960s. He was one of the "Freedom Riders," a group of black and white activists who rode interstate buses in the South to challenge segregation laws. Following one of these rides in May of 1961, he was arrested in Montgomery, Alabama, along with six other demonstrators, and charged with disturbing the peace. He was also arrested on several other occasions for direct actions against segregation laws. In addition to his direct participation in civil rights protests in the South, Coffin recruited and coordinated the work of many northern activists, particularly white students, and he was also a member of the Connecticut Advisory Board of the United States Commission on Civil Rights.
With the escalation of military actions in Vietnam, Coffin became heavily involved in the protests against the war. His activism began in 1965 with the formation of Americans For Re-appraisal of Far Eastern Policy, a group founded by Coffin and Allard Lowenstein that pushed for United States recognition of the People's Republic of China, the admission of China into the United Nations, and a cease-fire in Vietnam. Later that year, Coffin joined with a group of religious leaders, including John Bennett, Abraham Heschel, and Daniel Berrigan, to form the National Emergency Committee of Clergy Concerned About Vietnam. Coffin was named executive secretary of the organization. Initially, the group adopted a relatively moderate stance, recommending traditional political action and persuasion to affect change in U.S. policy toward Vietnam.
As the war in Vietnam escalated and lay people became interested in the work of the group, it changed its name to Clergy and Laity Concerned About Vietnam (CALCAV). CALCAV organized mobilizations, supported conscientious objectors and acts of civil disobedience, and urged members to offer draft resisters sanctuary in churches and synagogues. During this time, Coffin became a frequent speaker at anti-war rallies and a highly public figure. At an October 1967 protest in Boston, over 1000 draft resisters turned in their draft cards at a church service led by Coffin. Later that month, he and a number of other activists who had collected cards throughout the country, presented them to officials at the Department of Justice in Washington. As a result of these actions, Coffin was indicted along with Benjamin Spock, Marcus Raskin, Mitchell Goodman, and Michael Ferber on charges of conspiracy to aid draft resisters. They were convicted in 1968, but the charges were dropped in 1970 after the verdict was overturned on appeal. Coffin continued to protest against the war, and even traveled to North Vietnam in 1972 to accompany three released prisoners on their trip back to the United States. In the war's final stages and after its end, Coffin was an outspoken proponent of the granting of amnesty for draft resisters.
Throughout his tenure at Yale, Coffin's actions met with mixed reviews among Yale students, administrators, and alumni. Many older alumni and other conservative Yale factions called for his resignation or removal. While Kingman Brewster, Yale's president, disagreed with Coffin's methods of protest, particularly his stand on and involvement in civil disobedience, he stood behind Coffin's rights to free speech and held that Coffin's influence on Yale was generally positive. Coffin left Yale in December 1975, citing the need to remove himself from the academy in order to work on a global level for social justice, disarmament, and an end to hunger.
After leaving Yale, Coffin published his memoirs, Once to Every Man, and in November 1977, he became senior minister of Riverside Church in New York City. While at Riverside, Coffin dedicated himself to a variety of human rights causes, including world hunger, disarmament, homelessness, and poverty, among others. In 1979, he made headlines again by traveling to Iran to hold Christmas services for hostages being held in the American Embassy. In 1987, he left Riverside to become president of SANE/FREEZE, which was renamed Peace Action in 1993.
Coffin married Eva Rubinstein, a ballet dancer and the daughter of Arthur Rubinstein, in 1956 and they had three children: Amy, Alexander, and David. They were divorced in 1968. Coffin re-married in 1969, to Harriet Gibney; they divorced shortly after he left Yale. Coffin's third wife is Randy Wilson Coffin. After becoming president emeritus of SANE/FREEZE in the mid-1990s, Coffin moved to Vermont and continued to teach and lecture. He died of congestive heart failure at his home in Strafford, Vermont, on April 12, 2006.
Christianity and crisis; Amnesty -- United States; Civil disobedience; Civil Rights movements -- Southern States -- History -- 20th Century; Civil rights workers; Technical assistance, American -- Africa; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Conscientious objectors; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Draft resisters.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Chaplains; Bennett, John C. (John Coleman), 1902-1995; Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Brown, Robert McAfee, 1920-2001; Coffin, Catherine Butterfield, 1892-1982; Coffin, Ned; Coffin, William Sloane, Jr., 1924-2006; Dees, Morris, 1936-; Fernandez, Richard R. (Richard Ritter); Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Horton, Charlotte; Lovett, Sidney, 1890-1979; Magruder, Jeb Stuart, 1934-2014; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012; Miner, Joshua L.; Moyers, Bill D.; Neuhaus, Richard John, 1936-2009; Raskin, Marcus G., 1934-2017; Robinson, James H., 1907-1972; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-2011; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Americans for Reappraisal of Far Eastern Policy; Clergy and Laymen Concerned About Vietnam (U.S.); Institute for World Order; NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund; National Association of College and University Chaplains; National Conference for New Politics; Operation Crossroads Africa; Outward Bound, Inc; Peace Corps (U.S.); Riverside Church (New York, N.Y.); SANE, Inc; Southern Poverty Law Center; Student Christian Movement in New England; United States Commission on Civil Rights. Connecticut Advisory Committee; Vietnam Summer (Organization); Yale University. Chaplain's Office; Yale-China Association
- Correspondence, 1940-1983; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically within four sections: General, Family, Public Opinion Mail, and Speaking Engagements. Other correspondence of a topical nature exists in the Subject Files, Writings, and Yale Files series.
  General correspondence consists of letters exchanged between Coffin and civil rights leaders, Vietnam War and peace activists, university administrators, religious figures, politicians, students, and other individuals. The leading civil rights figures that corresponded with Coffin include Ralph Abernathy, Martin Luther King, Jr. and Coretta Scott King, but the correspondence is not particularly substantive. There is a substantial amount of correspondence with individuals involved in the anti-war movement, including Daniel Berrigan, Robert McAfee Brown, Rennie Davis, Richard Neuhaus, Marcus Raskin, Benjamin Spock, and Norman Thomas (see the description of Series II for a more detailed explanation of other correspondence and material related to the civil rights and anti-war movement). Letters between Coffin and several Yale University officials and faculty members, such as Kingman Brewster, A. Whitney Griswold, Reuben Holden, Louis Pollak, Richard Sewall, Gaddis Smith, and Norman Buck comprise another sizable portion of the series. The Brewster correspondence provides a particularly rich picture of Coffin's tenure as chaplain at Yale and of the relationship between these two high profile individuals. The section also includes a small amount of substantive correspondence with Yale students such as Joseph Lieberman, whose one letter describes his decision to decline admission to Skull and Bones, and Strobe Talbott, who writes detailed descriptions of his inner city work in Cleveland in the late 1960s (see Series III for other Yale related material). There is correspondence with religious leaders such as Reinhold Niebuhr, John C. Bennett, Sidney Lovett, and James Robinson and with politicians and public figures such as Jeb Magruder, George McGovern, Ralph Nader, Fred Rogers, and Studs Terkel. The McGovern correspondence includes documentation of Coffin's efforts on behalf of McGovern's presidential bid. Correspondence with colleagues in Outward Bound and the Peace Corps, including Fred Lanoue, Joshua Miner, Bill Moyers, Sargent Shriver, and Spencer Summers comprises another significant portion of the section. Other correspondence and documentation of these organizations can also be found in Series II.
  The bulk of the Family correspondence consists of incoming letters to Coffin from an earlier era in his life. Most of the letters from his mother Catherine Coffin and sister Margot Coffin date from the time Coffin served in the military, during and after World War II. Many of these letters were addressed to both Coffin and his brother Ned. Family correspondence also includes a small number of letters from Coffin's first wife, Eva, primarily written while Coffin was spending a summer in Guinea working with Operation Crossroads Africa volunteers.
  Public Opinion Mail consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence that comments on his public actions. These letters are arranged under the following topical headings: General, "Appeal for Theological Affirmation," Conspiracy Trial, Freedom Rides, and Glamour magazine article, each of which includes anti- and pro-Coffin folders. Although there are many more supportive letters, the critical correspondence is more dramatic and Coffin was more likely to answer his critics than supporters. The Conspiracy Trial correspondence comprises the most easily identified material in the collection that relates to Coffin's arrest, indictment, conviction, and successful appeal on charges of conspiring to aid draft resisters. The Freedom Rides correspondence contains similar types of materials.
  Speaking Engagements correspondence is arranged chronologically intwo sub-sections: Accepts and Declines. This section documents the great demand for Coffin as a public speaker and can be used to trace his appearances around the United States and abroad.
  - General
    - A, 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Abbot, John W., 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abernathy, Ralph David [includes photograph], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Armstrong, J. Sinclair, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Arnstein, Robert L., 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - B, 1956-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 11)
    - Barr, Browne, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bartholomew, Marshall, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Barton, H. Arnold, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bennett, John C., 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      General note
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 8 - 10
    - Berrigan, Daniel, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bilheimer, Robert S., 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Blackmer, Alan R., 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Boatwright, Helen, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Boyd, Malcolm, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Brademas, John, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bradford, J. Allyn, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1960-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 23 - 27)
    - Brown, Robert McAfee, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Buck, Norman S., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Burr, Ralph C., 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - C, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 31 - 35)
    - Campion, Thomas Baird, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - D, 1959-1975 (Box 2, Folder 37 - 40)
    - Davidson, Walter S., 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Davies, Alfred T., 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Davis, Rennie, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Dees, Morris
      See: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 202
    - E, 1959-1975 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Ellis, Jane, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - F, 1946-1975 (Box 3, Folder 46 - 49)
    - Fenger, T. Nick, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Ferber, Michael, 1969-1975 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Fernandez, Richard
      See: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 37 - 46
    - Fleishman, Joel L., 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Fromm, Erich, 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Fulbright, J. William, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - G, 1960-1975 (Box 3, Folder 55 - 59)
    - Gaensler, Anthony, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Gerson, Ralph J., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Giothe, Peter, 1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Gilden, Bert D., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Griswold, A. Whitney, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Guirey, Chinghiz [includes letters from Guirey's brother(?)], 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - H, 1959-1975 (Box 3, Folder 66 - 72)
    - Hall, Edward F., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Hallwachs, Marianne, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Handler, Wilfred, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Hanson, Joseph O., 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Hanson, Norwood Russell, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Hatcher, Robert, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Heister, John W., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Hillman, James, 1964-1974 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Holden, Rueben A., 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Holloway, Earl M., 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Holt, John, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Horton, Charlotte E., 1959-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Howe, Harold, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Hundertmark, Margaret, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - I, 1966-1975 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - J, 1962-1975 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Jenkins, Timothy L., 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Jones, Peter, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - K, 1960-1975 (Box 4, Folder 91 - 93)
    - Kaplan, Kivie, 1961-1970 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Kendrick, Gail T., 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Kennedy, Roger, 1959-1964 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - King, Coretta Scott, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 97)
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 114
    - King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - L, 1959-1975 (Box 4, Folder 99 - 102)
    - Lanoue, Fred, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Lieberman, Joseph I., 1963 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Loder, Theodore, 1963-1975 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Lovett, Sidney, 1960-1974 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Lowenstein, Albert, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Luce, Stephen, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - M, 1959-1975 (Box 5, Folder 109 - 115)
    - Mack, Maynard, 1961-1974 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Magruder, Jeb, 1959-1961, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Marshall, Moore, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Martin, Clyde, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Mattern, W. Gray, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - McClure, Alison, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - McGovern, George [includes campaign letter written by Coffin], 1965-1972 (Box 5, Folder 122 - 123)
    - McKee, Elmore M., 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Meagher, John C., 1975 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Milgram, Morris, 1963-1971 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Miller, Arthur, [1977] (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - Miller, J. Irwin, 1962-1975 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Miner, Joshua L., 1962-1972 (Box 5, Folder 129)
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 155 - 156
    - Moore, Paul, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Moyers, Bill, 1967, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 131)
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 158 - 163
    - Murphy, Lynne, 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - N, 1961-1970 (Box 5, Folder 133 - 134)
    - Nader, Ralph, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Napier, Davie, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Neuhaus, Richard J., 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1960, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - O, 1960-1975 (Box 6, Folder 139 - 140)
    - Oler, Clarke and Kim, 1960-1972 (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - P, 1960-1972 (Box 6, Folder 142 - 146)
    - Pelikan, Jaroslav J., 1963-1969 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Pollak, Louis H., 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Prashker, Betty A., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - Princeton University, 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Q, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - Quebedeaux, Richard, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - R, 1960-1975 (Box 6, Folder 153 - 157)
    - Raines, Robert A., 1960-1974 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Raskin, Marcus, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Redpath, Robert U., 1957-1972 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Riegal, Theodore Jr., 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Robinson, James H., 1963-1970 (Box 6, Folder 162)
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 147 - 154
    - Rogers, Fred, 1972, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Rogers, Talmadge Gregory, 1961-1972 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - Rose, Stephen C., 1962-1972 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - Russell, Robert M., 1964-1975 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - S, 1960-1975 (Box 7, Folder 167 - 175)
    - Scherer, Paul, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Schilling, Susan, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - Sewall, Richard B., 1963-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 178)
    - Shriver, Sargent, 1963-1970 (Box 7, Folder 179)
    - Smith, Gaddis, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Spock, Benjamin, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Summers, Spencer, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - T, 1957-1970 (Box 7, Folder 183 - 185)
    - Talbott, Strobe, Circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Tecla, Ruth, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 187)